Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, (7 boxes)
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints:, (192 items)
    - Mary and Dave Twedt taking a break during the construction of their home, McCook County, South Dakota, at the intersection of Highway 38 and County Road 431, July 1998, 56
      Dave is watchful of gathering storm clouds.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt, Gilbert Schuchardt and Danny Stone in front of Gilbert's home currently under construction in central Spencer, facing southwest, July 1998, 57
      The Twedts and I used to take a daily cruise through town as a way to take a break from working on their home. Dave called these little rides into town as "dress codes" or "inspecting the dress code" out of a tongue-in-cheek poke at the recent building code enforcements that followed the tornado. Dave was very vocal about the local politics.
    - Mary Twedt soon after finding a cushion for her patio furniture that had been missing since the tornado, July 1998, 58
      They had been cruising around Spencer one day in mid-July and saw it laying near the monument that had been placed to remember the Spencer School.
    - Dave Twedt taking a break and Mary Twedt sweeping in what will be the kitchen of their new home, the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, July 1998, 59
      The Twedts are rebuilding what once was the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. Dave bought this property less than one mile south of Spencer in 1986, several years before they bought a home in Spencer Proper.
    - Dave Twedt at work in the basement of what was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge, the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, July 1998, 60
    - Dave and Mary Twedt visiting the building site of their friends' Gilbert and JoAnne (right image) and the vacant lot where their house had been just a few blocks away (left image), Spencer 1998, 61
    - Mary Twedt riding on the pickup tailgate while Dave drives, 1/2 mile outside of Spencer, July 1998, 62
      The Twedts and I were on our way to burn trash at the end of the property. Mary is looking north towards Spencer.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt surveying the items recovered by the 5,000 volunteers who had combed Spencer, July 1998, 63
      5 days after a F-4 tornado destroyed 75% of the town organized volunteers then cleaned recovered items and set them on tables in the McCook County High School gym. The clothes that had been recovered were taken to the Springfield State Prison near Yankton where they were laundered in 200 pound capacity machines. Other items were cleaned and sorted by local organizations. I saw several people, including Dave and Mary, pick up and examine items that had been theirs prior to the tornado, then return them to the table. Dave said, "Some things are better left alone..." Upon walking into the gym for the first time, Nancy Webb said, "This is worse than the tornado." Many folks stood over the tables that had been covered with photographs from a period of at least 100 years and wept openly. It was the most powerful photo exhibit I had ever witnessed.
    - Mary Twedt holding three family photographs: Jessica (her and Dave's daughter) as a toddler in a high chair, Dave Twedt at age 4, and Mary at about 18 months, July 1998, 64
      Mary is wrapped in a quilt made by her grandmother. The Twedts and I were in the McCook Central High School gym where all the items recovered after the tornado by volunteers had been set out. There were 7-8 tables of nothing but photographs. The quilt and these photographs were among the many items that filled the gymnasium.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt in the McCook Cental High School gymnasium, July 1998, 65
      Clothing and objects that had been picked up by volunteers after the tornado were stacked on tables for Spencer residents. Over 5,000 volunteers combed Spencer on June 5, filling plastic bags with clothing, kitchen appliances, utensils, and many personal items. More than 7 tables were completely covered with carefully cleaned photographs. Mary is holding a quilt made by her grandmother.
    - Mary Twedt holding photographs that had been recovered by volunteers who combed Spencer following the March 30th tornado, McCook County High School gymnasium, July 1998, 66
      There were 7 tables of photographs laid edge to edge.
    - Mary Twedt holding up a can of beer to celebrate flowing water from the well, July 1998, 67
      The Twedts had been without running water for 45 days following the tornado. The Twedts are now rebuilding commercial property into a home. The property was once the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge with several hotel rooms. Dave Twedt bought this property in 1986, several years before they bought their home in Spencer about 1/2 mile to the north. The Twedts and I filled the dumpster (right) more than 3 times with material during the "gutting" process. The Twedts lived in the camper trailer for 6 months while working on their home.
    - Delphia Stuby with her granddaughter, Kallie Kennedy Rogers, on Delphia's lot in northwest Spencer, July 30, 1998, 68
      Kallie's father, Ed Rogers, dressed in white. Delphia's new home was built by South Dakota State Penitentiary inmates on site at the Springfield prison yard near Yankton. The interior is 768 sq ft, two bedrooms, one bath. Applicants must be 62 or older, or 18 with disability. The cost was $19,400, including delivery. Five of these homes were purchased in 1998/99 by families displaced by the tornado, three of which were placed in Spencer. Although Kallie and her parents moved to Michigan, Delphia said later, "Kallie is fifth generation Spencer."
    - Lloyd Webb during a break while working to re-hab Nancy Webb's childhood farmhouse, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, July, 1998, 69
      The Webb's house in Spencer proper was destroyed after receiving heavy tornado damage on May 30, 1998. They decided to use the insurance money to rebuild the farmhouse.
      Selenium toned gelatin silver print--two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Suzy Webb with bag of candy, Bridgette watches. Near the family farmhouse, July 1998, 70
      McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer.
    - Lloyd, Suzy and Nancy Webb inspect an antique farm wagon at an auction a few miles west of Spencer, South Dakota, September, 1999., 71
      They bought the wagon and later towed it home. I followed. The steel wheels made a wonderful noise rolling on the asphalt.
    - Lloyd Webb and I digging post-holes to put up barbed wire fencing. Horse bones at center and right of image, the north pasture on the family farm, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, September, 1998, 72
    - Dave Twedt covered with insulation during the rebuilding of their commercial property at the corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431. About 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota, September, 1998, 73
    - Mary Twedt sitting in the front passenger seat of their car, September, 1998, 74
      She and Dave passing the vacant lot where their house had been just a few months earlier in Spencer, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt rolling out insulation in what will be her and Dave's room, September, 1998, 75
      They are rebuilding commercial property to make their home about 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota. (Their home in Spencer was destroyed 5-30-98). This property was once "The Golden Pheasant", a restaurant/bar connected to several small hotel rooms.
    - Danny Stone propping up the under-side insulation of a mobile home his aunt owned, early September, 1998, 76
      She let him and Kara and Brandon (4 mo.) stay in the mobile home in Salem, South Dakota, while the Stones had their new home begin construction in Spencer.
    - Danny Stone preparing the canvas for his and Kara's wedding the following day. Veterans Park, Mitchell, South Dakota, September 18, 1998, 77
      Danny was the main canvas worker at Spencer Canvas in Mitchell.
    - The wedding of Danny Stone and Kara Arends, Mitchell, South Dakota, September 19, 1998, 78
      Officiating is the Reverend Ward Satterly of Spencer, South Dakota. He lost his wife in the May 30th tornado. She ran upstairs to try and save their dog as the tornado approached. The dog survived, but she perished... Kara's twin sister, Sara, pictured at right (Maid of honor).
    - Brandon Stone being prepared for his parent's wedding (Danny Stone/Kara Arends), Mitchell, South Dakota, September 19, 1998, 79
      He was only one month old when the tornado hit. His mother, Kara Arends, hovered over him in the basement and looked up to see the house beginning to life off the foundation. Minutes later, the entire house was gone.
    - After the wedding of Jenna Webb and Cliff Carlin, in the basement of the Church of the Nazarene, Mitchell, South Dakota, October 2, 1998, 80
      Lloyd Webb, left, and Nancy Webb holding Alexa Roth, the daughter of Vicki and Tony Roth... Vicky was a foster child who lived with the Webbs for many years.
    - Lloyd Webb power-chiseling through the concrete foundation of the farmhouse in preparation of installing a septic tank, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, October, 1998, 81
    - Interior wall on the first floor of the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, October, 1998, 82
      While Nancy's parents were still living in the farmhouse, a small fire broke out. The smoke from the fire blackened the wall, leaving ghost images from ceramic birds that had been hung. Her parents left the farmhouse not long after the incident.
    - Steve, a friend of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's, constructing an addition to the back of the original family farmhouse where Nancy and her brother, Steve, and sister, Myrta, were all raised, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles norht of Spencer, October, 1998, 83
      Lloyd, Nancy and Suzy lived in the camper trailer for several months, during construction.
    - Inside the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, October, 1998, 84
      The image on the left is a new downstairs bathroom/shower under construction. The image on the right is from an upstairs bedroom. The bookcase still holds books and toys from when Nancy, Myrta and Steve were children.
    - Richard Stone, during the process of installing an amplifier in his Chevy--a few miles north of Spencer at a friend's farm, McCook County, South Dakota, October, 1998, 85
      He was basically a runaway at this point, staying with friends, cutting school.
    - A photographer from People Magazine, making images of Dave and Mary Twedt walking where their house once stood in Spencer, South Dakota before the tornado hit on 5-30-98, 86
      (He did a page spread on the Twedts for the June, 1998 issue, visiting them just days after the tornado hit.)
    - A photographer from People Magazine, making images of Dave and Mary Twedt in front of the old Golden Pheasant Restaurant--where they are rebuilding the commercial property into a home, October 16, 1998, 87
      The intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431.
    - Mary Twedt, left, and her friend, Laura, planing hardwood floor pieces in the Twedt's basement, October, 1998, 88
      The hardwood flooring pieces were purchased at an auction that had featured many salvaged items from the closed Spencer School (several years prior).
    - Lloyd Webb on top of the farmhouse--the day several friends from his and Nancy's church came out to help clean up, McCook County--three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, November, 1998, 89
    - From the rooftop of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, three miles north of Spencer, mid-November, 1998, 90 (Box 22)
      A group of people from their church came to help do clean-up around the property.
    - Lloyd Webb grilling hamburgers and hot dogs for friends from the Church of the Nazarene (Mitchell, South Dakota) who are at the farmhouse to help with general clean-up and carpentry work, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, November, 1998, 91
    - A free Thanksgiving dinner for the residents of Spencer, South Dakota. McCook County High School gymnasium in Salem, South Dakota, 92
      This dinner was sponsored by local businesses a few days before Thanksgiving Day, 1998.
    - Danny Stone working on his house, Thanksgiving Day, 1998, 94
      The home builder he hired abandoned the project completely the month before, leaving the Stones with more than $35,000 debt. In other words, essentially taking $35,000 from their pockets.
    - Danny Stone with various insurance papers, Small Business Administration paperwork, building permits, etc, Spencer, South Dakota (following the 5-30-98 tornado), December 2, 1998, 95
      The Stone's original contractor abandoned him, leaving them with about $35,000 debt. Danny had to finish the house himself.
    - Danny Stone sanding the walls and ceilings in his home, Spencer, South Dakota, December 2, 1998, 96
      The builder he hired abandoned the job, leaving the Stones with more than $30,000 debt.
    - Lloyd Webb shoveling refuse from the newly re-built entry to the farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, the day before Thanksgiving, 1998, 97
      He taught me how to operate the backhoe and I got pretty good at it. However, two weeks later I accidently pulled up and severed the main power lines that had recently been buried (near the center of this image). I was digging a phone line and the hired electrician was the only other person there at the time. He said folks get killed doing that sort of thing. When Nancy came home later, I admitted my mistake. She laughed and said, "Don't worry about it! Lloyd does that sort of thing all the time." I held a flashlight late into the night while the electrician repaired it.
    - Dave Twedt making his famous sign of protest, 98
      It eventually read: THE BIBLE SAYS ASK AND YOU SHALL RECEIVE SARIN SAYS BE BROKE, BE HUMILIATED, BEG, AND MAYBE WE'LL HELP WITH DONATED MONEY. SARIN (Spencer Area Recovery and Interfaith Network) was a faith-based organization headed by the Rev. Mark Dickson, pastor of the Sun Prairie Baptist Church near Salem, South Dakota. Nearly 1 million dollars was collected in donations and SARIN was responsible for distributing the funds--which they did mainly to those who were under (or not) insured. The Twedts felt this was unfair. Dave made this sign in December, 1998 and it was stolen from his property on Christmas Eve, 1998.
    - Dave Twedt applying a band-aid to his finger, Mary Twedt watching, December, 1998, 99
      They are living in the garage area of the commercial property currently under re-construction. The "home" part of the building process will not be ready for several more weeks. They were nearly to their wit's end.
    - Mary Twedt tossing a sheet while making the bed, November 6, 1998, 100
      She and Dave are living in the garage area of the commercial property they are remaking into a home. The "home" part of the building is under construction. Here, they were surrounded by tools Dave used to rebuild cars. The sheet makes me think of a tornado.
    - Dave Twedt being interviewed by a television reporter from Sioux City, Iowa, about his sign (on the Jeep) protesting SARIN's method of spreading money donated by the public, McCook County, South Dakota, December, 1998, 101
      In front of his and Mary's home on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431.
    - (Left) Mary Twedt holding a photograph of the house in Spencer, South Dakota where she and her husband, Dave, lived at the time of the May 30, 1998 tornado. They were in the basement at the time. (Right) Dave Twedt holding a photograph of an 8 foot square sign he made to protest SARIN (Spencer Area Recovery and Interfaith Network), a faith based organization put in charge of allocating nearly 1 million dollars of donated money to help Spencer residents, February, 1999, 102
      Because the Twedts were well insured, like many others, SARIN helped those who were not insured--from the very beginning. Dave felt the money should have been distributed evenly. His sign was stolen on Christmas Eve, 1998. Two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Richard Stone applying the front window license to his aunt's mobile home in Salem, South Dakota, December, 1998, 103
      She has loaned out the use of the mobile home to Danny, Kara and their toddler, Brandon, and Richard while their new home in Spencer is under construction ten miles away.
    - Nancy Webb (far right) giving her husband, Lloyd, a ceramic figure of a man pushing his car out of a bank of snow, McCook County, South Dakota, three miles north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1998, 104
      She was teasing him for all the times he got farm and family vehicles stuck in the mud and snow. Nancy's sister, Myrta, is center--Christmas tree in background. The stairwell in the farmhouse.
    - Lloyd Webb working to thaw a water line in the north pasture, McCook County, South Dakota, the week between Christmas and New Year, 1998, 105
      A dead and frozen cow carcass, lower right.
    - Richard Stone looking into the basement bathroom that is under construction, Spencer, South Dakota, New Years Day, 1999, 106
      Behind him is the temporary cardboard door that closes onto the nails (right).
    - Richard Stone showing the ring he will give to his girlfriend. In a temporary room made for him in the southwest corner of the basement, Spencer, South Dakota, New Years Day, 1999, 107
    - On Interstate 90, heading east towards Sioux Fall, South Dakota after visiting Spencer on New Year's Day, 1999, 109
      My father's 1981 VW pickup. I found the doll head on the ground at the Webb's.
    - Suzy Webb sleeping, Lloyd driving, near Epiphany, South Dakota, January 9, 1999, 110
      We were going back to the Webb's farm after getting some furniture out of storage on a farm northeast of Spencer--some friends of the Webb's.
    - Nancy Webb stepping across the newly installed kitchen floor tiles, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000, 161
      Heating elements were placed beneath. The farmhouse is on the land that her grandfather homesteaded.
    - Nancy Webb wiping up the newly installed tiles in the farmhouse kitchen floor, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000, 162
      Heating elements were placed beneath.
    - Lloyd Webb working on the starter for his 1952 Chevy. Nancy's dog, Richard Nixon, nearby, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000, 163
      Suzy and Bridgette by the propane tank. At the farmhouse.
    - Powder and Suzy Webb running near the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, April, 2000, 164
      The concrete foundation (left) was part of the barn that had been destroyed by a tornado in 1969. The barn, Lloyd said, could be seen from Highway 38 nearly 4 miles away.
    - Kara and Brandon Stone during his 2nd birthday party, Spencer, South Dakota, May 1, 2000, 165
    - Jason Fredricks and Jessica Twedt after vows were exchanged. First Lutheran Church in downtown, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, September 30, 2000, 166
    - Lloyd Webb and his dog, Powder (one of several farm pets), on Lloyd's 45th birthday, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, March 23, 2002, 167
      Out in the barn, on the farm. It was around 25 to 30 degrees that day in the barn.
    - Dave Twedt with his granddaughter, Kaitlyn, on his 47th birthday. In the kitchen at home, Spencer, South Dakota, May 4, 2002, 168
    - Danny Stone in the northwest corner of his yard the day he turned 42 years old, Spencer, South Dakota, June 11, 2002, 169
    - Nancy and Lloyd Webb preparing to shoot at targets in the north pasture (Lloyd as a sergeant at the South Dakota State Penitentiary in Sioux Falls, July, 2002, 170
      Their marriage would begin to dissolve the following year. Three negatives printed consecutively.
    - Richard Stone in his basement apartment, the corner of South Dakota Avenue and 18th Street, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July, 2002, 171
      The building no longer exists--it was condemned and razed the following year.
    - Richard Stone in his basement apartment in Sioux Falls, South Dakota, late July, 2002, 172
      Unemployed and behind in his rent.
    - Nancy Webb making pizza dough at the farmhouse, 3 miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, May 17, 2003, 173
      We were celebrating Nancy's 47th birthday (May 16).
    - Nancy Webb helping her grandson, Isaac, with his pedal car, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer at the family farm, May 17, 2003, 174
      This was Saturday, May 17, 2003 and we were celebrating Nancy's 47th birthday (May 16). The sink, to the left, was at one time down the hall from my Sioux Falls studio space. I used it when washing prints.
    - Lloyd Webb and his grandson, Issac, at the barn entrance, McCook County--three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, May 17, 2003 (Nancy's birthday party), 175
      Lloyd was pulling ticks off Powder (the white dog) and Issac was smashing them. Richard Nixon, Nancy's dog, watches.
    - Kaitlyn Ann (Peanut) at her dance school's dress rehearsal, on stage at the Riad Shrine Auditorium in downtown Sioux Falls, South Dakota, May 17, 2003, 176
    - With Dave and Mary Twedt's home to my back--facing east/southeast, corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431, May 30, 2003, 177
      Five years to the day when a F-4 tornado destroyed most of Spencer, South Dakota (about 1/2 mile north of this location). Winds to 50 mph were reported in Sioux Falls on the day this photograph was made.
    - Paityn, the smallest, and Kaitlyn, Jessica (left), Doris Westerman (the kids' great-grandmother/Mary's mother) and Mary Twedt (right), 1512 S. Olive Drive, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2003, 178
      Katie's 4th birthday. In Al and Doris Westerman's backyard.
    - Kaitlyn Anne Fredricks ("Peanut") at a party for her 4th birthday, July 19, 2003, 179
      We are at Al and Doris Westerman's in Sioux Falls, South Dakota. The Westermans are Mary Twedt's parents, making them Peanut's great-grandparents. Mary is left, with Paityn over her shoulder.
    - Kaitlyn Anne (Peanut) and Paityn, right, running in Dave and Mary Twedt's front area, the corner of County Road 431 and South Dakota Hwy 38, McCook County, South Dakota, May 30, 2004, 180
      Six years to the day from the Spencer tornado.
    - Kaitlyn with her dolls, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2004, 181
      We were celebrating Peanut's 5th birthday (July 19). This was the same year Jessica divorced Kaitlyn's father, Jayson Fredricks.
    - Jessica, shortly before marrying Tony Byre in Brandon, South Dakota, May 14, 2005, 182 (Box 23)
      Jessica is the only child of Dave and Mary Twedt.
    - Kaitlyn, with arms outstretched, at Jessica and Tony's wedding reception. (Her mother's second marriage.) Near Beaver Creek, Minnesota, May 17, 2005, 183
      Jessica and Tony Byre were married earlier that day in Brandon, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt sweeping up after 100 mph straight line winds blew the roof off their home the night before (August 2), McCook County, South Dakota, August 4, 2004, 184
    - Kaitlyn Fredricks and Mary Twedt (Kaitlyn's grandmother) atop the Twedt's home, June, 2005, 185
      Dave and Mary were in the process of rebuilding a part of their roof that had been blown off the year before (Spencer can be seen in the distance).